Chapter 58. Brit.
Steering northeastward from the Croettes, we fell in with vast meadows
of Brit, the minute yellow substance upon which the right whale largely
feeds, for leagues and leagues had undulated round us, so that we seemed to
be sailing through boundless fields of ripe and golden wheat. On the second
day, numbers of right whales were seen, who, secure from the attack of a sperm
whaler like the Peekquad, with open jaws sluggishly swam through the Brit, which
adhering to the fringing fibers of that wondrous Venetian blind in their mouths,
was in that manner separated from the water that escaped at the lip.
as morning mowers who side by side slowly and seethingly advanced their
sides through the long wet grass of marshy mess. Even so these monsters swam
making a strange grassy cutting sound and leaving behind them endless swaths
of blue upon the yellow sea.
Footnote. That part of the sea known among whalemen as the Brazil banks does
not bear that name as the banks of Newfoundland do because of there being
shallows and soundings there, but because of this remarkable meadow-like
appearance caused by the vast drifts of Brit continually floating in those
latitudes where the right whale is often chased. End of footnote.
But it was only the sound they made as they parted the Brit, which at all
reminded one of mowers, seen from the mast heads, especially when they paused
and were stationary for a while, their vast black forms looked more like
lifeless masses of rock than anything else. And as in the great hunting
countries of India, the stranger at a distance will sometimes pass on the
plains recumbent elephants without knowing them to be such, taking them for
bare blackened elevations of the soil, even so often for him who for the first
time beholds this species of Leviathans on the sea. And even when recognized at
last, their immense magnitude renders it very hard really to believe that such
bulky masses of overgrowth can possibly be instinct in all parts with the same
sort of life that lives in a dog or a horse.
Indeed, in other respects, you can hardly regard any creatures of the deep
with the same feelings that you do of those of the shore. For though some old
naturalists have maintained that all creatures of the land are of their kind
in the sea, and though taking a broad general view of the thing, this may very
well be, yet coming to specialties, where, for example, does the ocean
furnish any fish that in disposition answers to the sagacious kindness of the
dog? The oursed shark alone can in any generic respect be said to bear
comparative analogy to him. But though to landsmen in general the native
inhabitants of the seas have ever been regarded with emotions unspeakably
unsocial and repelling, though we know the sea to be an everlasting terror
incognita, so that Columbus sailed over numberless unknown worlds to discover
his one superficial western one. Though by vast odds, the most horrific of all
mortal disasters have immemorialally and indiscriminately befallen tens and
hundreds of thousands of those who have gone upon the waters. Though but a
moment's consideration will teach that however baby man may brag of his science
and skill and however much in a flattering future that science and skill
may augment, yet forever and forever to the crack of doom the sea will insult
and murder him and pulverize the statiest stiffest frigot he can make.
Nevertheless, by the continual repetition of these very impressions,
man has lost that sense of the full awfulness of the sea which Aboriginally belongs to it.
The first boat we read of floated on an ocean that with Portuguese vengeance had
wellemed a whole world without leaving so much as a widow. That same ocean
rolls now. That same ocean destroyed the wrecked ships of last year. Yay! Foolish
mortals, Noah's flood is not yet subsided. Twothirds of the fair world it yet covers.
Wherein differ the sea and the land that a miracle upon one is not a miracle upon
the other. Predternatural terrors rested upon the Hebrews, when under the feet of
Kora and his company the live ground opened and swallowed them up forever.
Yet not a modern sun ever sets, but in precisely the same manner, the live sea
swallows up ships and crews.
But not only is the sea such a foe to
man who is an alien to it, but it is also a fiend to its own offspring, worse
than the Persian host who murdered his own guests, sparing not the creatures
which itself hath spawned. Like a savage tigress that tossing in the jungle
overlays her own cubs, so the sea dashes even the mightiest whales against the
rocks and leaves them there side by side with the split wrecks of ships. No
mercy, no power, but its own controls it. Panting and snorting like a mad
battle steed that has lost its rider, the masterless ocean overruns the globe.
Consider the subtleness of the sea, how its most dreaded creatures glide
underwater, unapparent for the most part, and treacherously hidden beneath
the loveliest tints of azure. Consider also the devilish brilliance and beauty
of many of its most remorseless tribes as the dainty embellished shape of many
species of sharks. Consider once more the universal cannibalism of the sea,
all whose creatures prey upon each other, carrying on eternal war since the world began.
Consider all this, and then turn to this green, gentle, and most dosile earth.
Consider them both, the sea and the land, and do you not find a strange
analogy to something in yourself? For as this appalling ocean surrounds the
verdant land, so in the soul of man, there lies one insular Tahiti full of
peace and joy, but encompassed by all the horrors of the half-known life. God
keep thee. Push not off from that aisle.
Thou canst never return.